A Guide to the Tracy W. McGregor Autograph Collection, ca. 1599-1947
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Tracy W. McGregor Autograph Collection, ca. 1599-1947
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10547
This collection consists of 1,725 items in 11 Hollinger boxes, 80 slipcases and three oversize boxes (OS Boxes X-1 through X-3).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was acquired through gift and purchase, 1938-present.
Organization
This collection is comprised of many different accession numbers and additions to the original McGregor purchases. It is arranged alphabetically by the name of the principal correspondent or author but the accession number will also be noted in the summary of the item. Provenance information about each accession can be obtained from its control folder or Virgo record. Only small autograph collections belonging to the McGregor Library are included in this guide.
The collection is divided into three series:
1) Letters and Manuscripts:
Admiralty Office of Great Britain through Henry Clay (Box 1)
Ernest Hartley Coleridge through Samuel G. Drake (Box 2)
Earl of Dunmore through Florida (Box 3)
Ebenezer Foote through Walter King (Box 4)
Harry Lauder through James Madison (Box 5)
James Madison through Hugh Mercer (Box 6)
James Monroe through Philip Slaugher (Box 7)
Theodore Spenser through the Wormeley Family (Box 8)
George Wythe and Robert Carter Nicholas Law Firm Papers (Box 9)
2) Bound Volumes (Boxes 9- 11)
3) Numbered Slipcase Items #1-77 and N, O, P
Contents List
- SERIES I. LETTERS & MANUSCRIPTS
  - British Navy Register, "A List of His Majesty's Navy, Showing the Dimensions and Age of every Ship therein." Navy Office, 1st June 1777" Admiralty Office 1777-1799, AMs (Box 1)
    #10927
  - Draft of a Confidential Report to the Lords of the Admiralty, Whitehall 1780 Feb 23, AD, 6p. on 2 l. (Box 1)
    Reports of intelligence information concerning the vulnerability of the Spanish Territories in the region of the Gulf of Mexico and plans for British forces to exploit this situation and to protect the British interests in Pensacola and the Province of West Florida against the possible attacks of the Spanish Governors of Cuba and New Orleans. #6209
  - American Revolutionary War Document: Pay Roll of Captain Charles Porterfield's Company, 11th Virginia Regiment of Foot, Continental Army, commanded by Colonel Daniel Morgan 1778 Oct (Box 1)
    #6164
  - American Revolutionary War Document: Muster Roll, "Artillery Park near Morristown," for the Continental Artillery, commanded by Colonel Charles Harrison of Virginia, and consisting of companies commanded by Virginia captains, James Pendleton, Drury Ragsdale, and Whitehead Coleman, and signed by Pendleton and General Henry Knox 1780 Mar (Box 1)
  - Commission appointing Sir Edmund Andros, governor of "Dominion of New England" granted by King James II of Great Britain 1686 May, AMs, 17p. (Box 1)
    #10547-i
  - George Bancroft to James Madison 1836 Apr 8, ALS, 2p. (Box 1)
    GB thanks JM for his hospitality at Montpelier and sends a copy of the first volume of the Notices of the War of 1812 by John Armstrong; #2824-a
  - James Phinney Baxter, Isle of Wight, to "Dear Gould" 1885 Aug 20, ALS, 4p. on 2 l. (Box 1)
    This letter concerns financial arrangements, his reception by Queen Victoria, hearing a sermon by Charles H. Spurgeon, and travel through the British Isles and Europe; #10547
  - Henry H. Edes, Boston, to James Phinney Baxter, with an invitation, November 7 1904, from the Council of the Colonial Society of Massachusetts 1904 Nov 23, ALS, 3p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
    Discusses the annual dinner for the Colonial Society and requests Baxter nominate the Reverend John Carroll Perkins to membership; #10547
  - Not That I Would Boast by Max Beerbohm, with autograph corrections & instructions by Beerbohm 1927 Apr 4, Galley proof, 8p. (Box 1)
    #10547-b
  - Max Beerbohm, Upper Berkeley Street, to "Gentlemen" 1901 May 31, ALS, 3p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
    [Agrees to write an essay on Oscar Wilde whom he knew personally for some years and sets his financial terms for the work; #10547-b
  - Max Beerbohm, Upper Berkeley Street, to [Arthur Bingham] Walkley 1903 Nov 4, ALS, 4p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
    Refuses to advise about a dance and includes a caricature by him; #10547-b
  - Max Beerbohm, Upper Berkeley Street, to [Frances Eldridge] Walkley 1909 Jun 25, ALS, 2p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
    Declines an invitation due to a prior engagement; #10547-b
  - Max Beerbohm, Rapallo, Italy, to [Arthur Bingham] Walkley 1911 Oct 15, ALS, 2p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
    Sends a presentation copy of his recently completed novel about Oxford, Zuleila Dobson, to Walkley; #10547-b
  - Max Beerbohm, Rapallo, Italy, to [Arthur Bingham Walkley] 1922 Feb 26, ALS, 2p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
    Thanks Walkley for defending him in his Times article and hopes that his own review of Walkley's book in The Times did not annoy him; mentions purchasing a house in Italy, Walkley's account of sitting between G.K. Chesterton and Hilaire Belloc on a social occasion, and the impending arrival of Theodore Byard in Italy; and invites the Walkleys to visit him in Italy; #10547-b
  - Max Beerbohm, Rapallo, Italy, to [Arthur Bingham Walkley] 1926 Sep 18, ALS, 2p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
    Regrets reading that Walkley has suffered a relapse in his recent illness; urges a rapid convalescence, "What a nuisance and curse one's manner-for-print is when one is writing a letter! Would that I could write in the simple straightforward 'awfully-sorry' strain which would express my feelings so much more accurately!"; and shares an anecdote about bath-chairs; #10547-b
  - Max Beerbohm, Rapallo, Italy, to Editor of The Daily Heraldn.y. May 21, 2 ALS, 2p. on 2 l. (Box 1)
    Encloses another letter to be printed in the paper in response to criticism of himself by J.Q.X., a Daily Herald writer, who accused him of vulgarity in the drawing of a Labor Minister for Education "scoffing at a penurious poet who, declaring himself a 'worker,' has applied to him for aid." About vulgarity, Beerbohm writes, "Vulgarity has its uses. Vulgarity often cuts ice which refinement scrapes at vainly. And I like to think that some of the Labor leaders who have read J.Q.X. 's account of my shocking little drawing will visit the Leicester Galleries and be shocked themselves -- shocked even into realizing, as they do not yet seem to have realized, that the well-being of skilled and unskilled manual workers is not quite all that matters."; #10547-b
  - Max Beerbohm, Upper Berkeley Street, to Frances Eldridge Walkley Friday, ALS, 2p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
    Thanks her for the lovely flowers and agrees on a date, October 9; #10547-b
  - 1807-1808, AMs, 39p. (Box 1)
    Disjointed Treatise by Joshua Belding, relying heavily on visionary revelation and Scripture, proposing programs for land distribution, fiscal reform, and the formation of a national bank; urges peace with England and the divestment of Freemason wealth; and includes a discussion of the Burr-Wilkinson Conspiracy; #10547-br
  - Map of Carolina and Georgia by Jacques Nicolas Bellin 1755 (Box 1)
    #4442
  - Arthur Christopher Benson to Mr. Gleason 1917 Mar 1, ALS, 1p. (Box 1)
    Thanks Gleason for his "vivacious & encouraging note"; #10547-v
  - Documents of Sir William Berkeley concerning his governorship of Virginia and his conduct during Bacon's Rebellion 1674-1677, 4 ADS (Box 1)
    #2596-a
  - Augustine Birrell to "Dear Seton" 1921 Feb 3, ALS, 2p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
    Donates his copy of Orbiter Dicta for fund raising purposes; mentions that his books are out of print, except for a "cheap" edition of Selections; comments on the difference between the first and second editions of Orbiter Dicta and how booksellers advertise the first edition as including, "the suppressed verses" to increase its sale value; and declines to sign the book because he dislikes authors' inscriptions; #10547-w
  - 4 Photographic reproductions of illustrations from the French Book of Hours n.d., Black & white (Box 1)
    #38-728
  - Mrs. Margaret Downing Brainard to Frederick S. Dellenbaugh 1914 Jun 29, ALS, 4p. on 2 l. (Box 1)
    Discusses, William Lewis Manly (1820-1903), his character and death; mentions that before Death Valley in '49 was printed in book form, her husband published it in the Santa Clara Valley weekly and describes Judge Brainard's method of editing the work for publication; her plans to record California pioneer stories and memoirs; and her review of Edward Eggleston's book, The Ultimate Solution of the Negro Problem; #10547-z
  - Associates of Dr. Thomas Bray, papers related to their work in the United States, especially for a school for African-American children at Williamsburg, including correspondence, much of it to Robert Carter Nicholas and Dr. Thomas Dawson; printed accounts of the proceedings and designs of the Associates; lists of rules for both the owners of the African-American scholars and their teachers; extracts from Mr. Nelson's "Preface to the Festivals and Fasts"; and lists of subscriber names who funded the instruction of "Negroes in the Christian faith" 1757-1773, 25 items (Box 1)
    #564
  - Marquis of Buckingham [George Nugent Temple Grenville] to J. King, with note from King to [Sir Evan Nepean (1751-1822), Under Secretary for War] on back page 1794 Apr 25, ALS, 3p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
    Mentions his discussion with William Pitt and Mr. Dunlap concerning General John Graves Simcoe (1752-1806) and the Queen's Rangers stationed in Canada; urges Simcoe's promotion to brigadier general; and inquires about David Fanning; in his note to Nepean, King agrees that the Queen's Rangers must be kept in Canada and used in occupying York or some other port on Lake Eire and that Simcoe be given the rank of brigadier general; #10547-y
  - Edmund Burke (1729-1797) to "Dear Sir," 1778 Mar 17, ALS, 1p.; with typescript copy (Box 1)
    Discusses the Fishery in the Severn, encloses copies of the King's Message to the House of Commons respecting the declaration of the French Ambassador which accompanied it; and expresses his reservations about going to war with France; #10547-aa
  - Manuscript fragments of four lines of "The Two Dogs" and four lines of the glossary of the first Edinburgh edition of the Poems by Robert Burns n.d., AMs (Box 1)
    #10547-ab
  - Two printed copies of an engraved portrait of Robert Burns and a Mezzotint portrait of his sister, Isabella Burns n.d. (Box 1)
  - Ohio Documents concerning the Burr Conspiracy 1806, photostatic copy; originals are at the Western Reserve Historical Society (Box 1)
    #2595
  - Four Documents and a news clipping (1855) concerning the Aaron Burr Conspiracy, including a letter from George Morgan to General Presley Neville, 1806 Sep 2, requesting a meeting to discuss what he knows about "a most nefarious scheme against our country," which was endorsed by Pennsylvania Chief Justice William Tilghman. Tilghman also wrote a two page memorandum concerning his findings at the meeting with Morgan about Burr, dated 1806 November 18, in Philadelphia. Also present is a letter from Burr's lawyer, John Wickham, to George Carter, 1808 July 9, and an undated letter from Margaret Blennerhasset to Dudley Woods ordering supplies from Marietta. 1806-1808, 1855 (Box 1)
    #3639
  - Aaron Burr to John Hopkins, with a receipt from John Hopkins to Paul Carrington, November 16, 1800 1807 Aug 9, ALS, 1p. (Box 1)
    Discusses his trial for treason; #5409
  - Document originating from U.S. Senator Jonathan Dayton (1760-1824) concerning the Burr Conspiracy; probably used as testimony at Burr's trial in 1807, and believed to have come from the papers of Virginia governor, Littleton W. Tazewell, and includes 8 pages in one volume sewn together [pre 1807], ADS, 8p. in 1 vol. (Box 1)
    #5726
  - Andrew Gregg to James Hamilton, re the trial of Senator John Smith (1735-1816), an associate of Aaron Burr 1808 Jan 5, 8, 2 ALS (Box 1)
    #2806
  - "The Return" by John Burroughs n.d., AMsS, 1p. (Box 1)
    #38-735
  - John Burroughs to "Dear Sir" 1890 Jan 29, ALS, 1p. (Box 1)
    Discusses his work, "None of my outdoor essays were published in book form previous to Wake Robin. My last book, not included in your list is called Indoor Studies."; #38-735
  - John Burroughs to Russell A. Bowers n.y. Jan 15, ALS, 1p. (Box 1)
    Quotes from Emerson's Journal his remark about Walt Whitman and his contributions to American literature; #38-735
  - John Burroughs to the Editor of The Century Magazine1917 Dec 3, ALS, 1p. (Box 1)
    Asks when the magazine plans on using his paper called "Nature Lore," as he wishes to use it in a volume of essays to be published next year; #38-735
  - John Burroughs to May Cline 1891-1923, 4 ALS (Box 1)
    Discusses her "sermon" to him; his being full of sentiment and imagination; his sensitivity to people, nature, the weather, the seasons, and his household, but not enough on the spiritual side; his lack of belief in ghosts, spiritualism, telepathy, and immortality; Walt Whitman's comment on immortality; and describes his vineyards, his stone house, his daily routine, his reading material, and his walks (1891 Nov 27, incomplete); Dr. Clara Barnes writes to Cline thanking her for her help and discussing John Burroughs health and death (1923 Feb); thanks her for the painting and mentions his trip to the maple camp at Roxbury, New York (Mar 26); and writes he is in the midst of the grape harvest; mentions the novel of his friend Miss Sprague of Ohio, The Earnest Trifler; and urges her to study the best authors, which did not include Donnelly (Sep 3); #38-735
  - John Burroughs to [Richard Watson] Gilder [1903]-1905, 2 ALS (Box 1)
    Asks if he would like to see his paper "Current Misconceptions in Natural History" refused by The Atlantic as too controversial (1903); and writes that he doesn't see anything wrong in his letter to Walt Whitman, has just returned from Mr. Whitehead's Arts & Handicrafts Colony at Woodstock, New York, and enjoyed his stay with the Gilders at [Faun] Brook Farm (1905); #38-735
  - John Burroughs to [Robert Underwood] Johnson 1894 Jan 31, ALS (Box 1)
    Asks is he is interested in publishing Notes of a Seaso n which he needs to use in a book for June; #38-735
  - John Burroughs to Mr. Miller 1893-[1905?], 6 ALS (Box 1)
    Lists various portraits and photographs done of him over the years and mentions his large grape harvest (1893 Oct 25); has substituted a better photograph of himself with his autograph to be sent to Joaquin Miller (1894 Sep 11); has never heard of the editors of Walt Whitman to whom Miller has referred (1897 Sep 26); accepts his offer of a copy of The Natural History of Alaska(Jan 23); acknowledges the receipt of a sketch (Oct 5); and has written in the book as Miller requested, has a copy of the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass and is busy looking back over his Alaska trip with the Harriman Expedition ([1905?] Oct 27); #38-735
  - John Burroughs to Mrs. [J.M.] Patten n.y. Feb 11, ALS, 1p. (Box 1)
    Thanks her for her approval of his sentiments concerning women and money, although the reporter was not very accurate in reporting his talk; #38-735
  - P.M. Barnard to John Harrison concerning bibliographical inquiries about the first issue of Manfred by George Gordon Byron with copies of letters from Thomas J. Wise concerning variants of Manfred 1928, 6 TLS (Box 1)
    #10547-ac
  - Joseph C. Cabell to John Hartwell Cocke 1826 Jul 4, ALS, 2p. (Box 1)
    Describes in great detail the events preceding the death of Thomas Jefferson and his wish to live until the fourth of July; #5644
  - Thomas Carlyle to Jane Baillie (Welsh) Carlyle 1841 [Apr 30], ALS, 2p. (Box 1)
    Written on the reverse side of a letter from Mrs. Welsh to him, about which Carlyle asks advice; and describes moonshine walks and the fine weather; #10547-c
  - Thomas Carlyle to Leigh Hunt [ca. 1850], ALS, 2p. (Box 1)
    Inviting him to tea with Ben Nelson and possibly John Stuart Mill; #10547-c
  - Thomas Carlyle to "Dear Jenny" 1859 Jan 7, ALS, 4p. (Box 1)
    Writes to his sister about family news, his work on his book concerning Frederick the Great, sends a gift, and mentions the health of his wife, Jane; #10547-c
  - Thomas Carlyle to "Dear Sir" 1873 Nov 14, ALS, 5p. (Box 1)
    Discusses his correspondent's pamphlet concerning the modern life in England and offers literary advice and encouragement; #10547-c
  - William Edward Hartpole Lecky to Mr. Lowell 1880 [Nov?] 8, ALS, 2p. (Box 1)
    Writes concerning an anecdote re Thomas Carlyle; #10547-c
  - Etching of Thomas Carlyle in his garden at Chelsea by C.O. Murray based on a painting by Mrs. Allingham n.d. (Box 1)
    #10547-c
  - Lewis Carroll [C.L. Dodgson] to Mrs. Stevens 1891 Apr 5, ALS, 4p.; with envelope (Box 1)
    Has been printing visiting cards for Enid so she can leave them along with those of her mother as they leave, sends six calling cards with six kisses and asks when she can visit him alone and accompany him on a trip to Eastbourne; #10547-ad
  - Appendix for The Natural History of Carolina, Florida, and the Bahama Islands by Mark Catesby, with notes by Cromwell Mortimer, Secretary of the Royal Society 1747-8 Feb 18, AMsS, 15p. (Box 1)
    #4530
  - Autograph of Samuel Chase, American jurist, Federalist, and signer of the Declaration of Independence n.d., ADS (Box 1)
    #10547-av
  - Four Civil War Maps, three by Captain V.C. Von Koerber, concerning cavalry engagements between General Alfred Pleasonton and J.E.B. Stuart (1863 Jun 9, 17, 21); and one anonymous concerning Picket Posts in King George County, Virginia 1863 & n.d. (Box 1)
    #5447, -a
  - Civil War Reports by Lt. David F. Dobie, Company H, 118th Regiment, New York Volunteers, Yorktown, Virginia, re Ordnance and Ordnance Stores 1864, 9 items (Box 1)
    #10547-dj
  - Clara May Jane Clairmont to Leigh Hunt 1852 Aug 30, ALS, 4p. (Box 1)
    Pleased to have a letter from an associate of her youth, expresses her concern for his son, Henry Leigh, and his financial difficulties, remarks upon the lack of sincerity and truthfulness in the young, and her own straitened financial condition due to the death of her brother who left six children with no financial resources; #10547-af
  - 1808, 14 ALS (Box 1)
    Letters testifying as to the fair treatment of the settlers in the Green River section of Kentucky and to the good character of General Green Clay; #2291-a
  - Henry Clay Letters to James Brown, [James Madison?], A. [Pierse], Nathan Sargent, Joseph Story, and A.W. Stowe 1813-1849, 23 ALS (Box 1)
    Secretary of State Henry Clay's letters to James Brown, U.S. minister to France (1823-1829), generally concern foreign affairs and politics, but particularly discuss the Louisiana Treaty and its effects on the collection of alien duties from France and the affair at Rio de Janeiro, Brazil (1827 May 30); the re-election chances of President John Quincy Adams (1828 May 17 & Oct 11); the generosity of Brown to Mrs. Hart & Mrs. Price and the possible candidacy of John C. Calhoun for the Presidency (1831 Apr 8 & Dec 18, 1832 Mar 28); public life and Andrew Jackson (1831 Aug 24); Cholera epidemic & politics (1832 Oct 23); the future abolition of slavery in the United States (1833 Jul 7); concerns over Brown's health (1833 Sep 8); Other topics include: the appointment of a postmaster in Lexington, Kentucky (1813 Dec 11); slavery and the fall in the price of cotton (1837 Apr 26); discusses the prospects of the Whig Party in the elections with Nathan Sargent (1838 Aug 11, 1839 Oct 29, 1842 May 21 & Jul 31, 1843 Sep 2 & 19, 1846 Apr 28); the retirement of Supreme Court Justice Joseph Story (1845 Feb 9) and the Free Soil question facing the new President (1849 Feb 16); #991
  - Henry Clay to Thomas Law 1829 May 28, ALS, 2p. (Box 1)
    Discusses land claims of Mr. Blane in Kentucky and disappointment in President Andrew Jackson; #2801
  - Henry Clay to John L. Lawrence 1830-1848, 8 ALS (Box 1)
    Discusses the importance of systematic effort in politics to insure success and New York politics (1830 Dec 13); the importance of defeating Andrew Jackson in the 1832 election for president (1831 Mar 7; Apr 13); the selection of the Whig party candidate for vice president and Daniel Webster (1843 Oct 5); his concerns pertaining to possible war with Great Britain over Oregon and with Mexico over Texas (1845 Apr 30);and the differences between General Zachary Taylor and General William Henry Harrison (1848 Jun 16); #5828
  - Henry Clay to Brantz Mayer 1832 Jun 17, ALS, 2p. (Box 1)
    Answers his request for information about Daniel Boone, whom Clay did not know personally, by giving him advice about who to read or contact; #4990
  - Henry Clay to Secretary of War [Joel R. Poinsett] and Richard Henry Wilde 1840 & 1847, 2 ALS (Box 1)
    Inquires whether arms belonging to the state of Kentucky but used by the U.S. government can be replaced without a special act of Congress (1840); and discusses a legal case with Wilde (1847); #2290
  - Henry Clay to Daniel Gardner 1840 Jul 7, ALS, 1p. (Box 1)
    Informs Gardner that he can find his opinion on the undisclosed subject of his letter in the Panama instructions contained in [Niles?] Register, 1829, and in the State papers of Congress; #2291
  - Legal brief in case of Joseph Ray, in handwriting of Henry Clay; #2467 [1843], AD, 7p. (Box 1)
  - Henry Clay to Henry White, David S. Brown, John B. Meyers, Francis N. Buck, and William Reynolds 1844-1847, 4 ALS (Box 1)
    Discusses his feelings about the operations of the National Clay Club and the political support of the citizens of Philadelphia for himself (1844 Mar 17; 1845 Dec 16; 1847 Aug 21); and his concern for the election for governor of Pennsylvania (1844 Sep 19); #1649
  - Henry Clay to George Davis 1844 Aug 31, ALS, 1p. (Box 1)
    Discusses the prospect of success in the Presidential election in November; #2802
  - Ernest Hartley Coleridge to George Grove 1889-1890, 2 ALS (Box 2)
    Acknowledges the receipt of a volume of Coleridgeiana; comments on the information in it; discusses engravings and miniatures of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and his friends; and mentions Ward Thomas Poole; #10547-ag
  - Samuel Taylor Coleridge to James Montgomery, written on the second leaf of Prospectus of the Friend 1809 (Box 2)
    For item see: McGregor Broadside 1809 .C65; #10547-ah
  - Notes on the Sacraments, formerly laid in The Book of Common Prayer by [Thomas Stevenson?] [ca. 1761], AMs, 1p. (Box 2)
    #10547-ae
  - "Joseph Conrad The History of His Books" by Richard Curle n.d., TM, 17p.; with autograph corrections in Conrad's hand, 17 pages numbered 1-16 (Box 2)
    #38-732
  - Joseph Conrad to Sidney Colvin 1918 Oct 21, ALS, 2p. (Box 2)
    Promises copies of Youth and History of the British Army; has just heard this morning that his son Borys is in the hospital after being "slightly gassed"; and "Jessie is firm as a rock, what with her pride in the boy, her love for me and her profound unquestioning patriotism"; #38-732
  - Joseph Conrad to Sidney Colvin 1920 Jan 20, ALS, 4p. (Box 2)
    Has been suffering a long bout of very black depression and illness, including a much swollen wrist which has allowed him to spend but a little time in pruning the text of The Rescue; expresses his happiness that Colvin's Croquis des Personnes are to be collected and published; and mentions that Jessie is making marvelous progress; #38-732
  - Joseph Conrad to his literary friend and advisor, Edward Garnett [1895 Mar 8], ALS, 4p. (Box 2)
    Sends four chapters of The Outcast his second book and asks his advice about different words in the beginning of Chapter XII; #38-732
  - Joseph Conrad to Edward Garnett [1896 Apr 13], AL, 2p. (Box 2)